<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Kyle N. Payne</title>
 <link href="http://kylenpayne.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://kylenpayne.github.io/"/>
 <updated>2015-12-20T22:20:32-06:00</updated>
 <id>http://kylenpayne.github.io</id>
 <author>
   <name>Kyle N. Payne</name>
   <email>knpayne2@illinois.edu</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Why you should write me a letter of recommendation</title>
   <link href="http://kylenpayne.github.io/2015/12/20/why-recommend/"/>
   <updated>2015-12-20T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <id>http://kylenpayne.github.io/2015/12/20/why-recommend</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;script scr=&quot;http://cdn.mathjax.org/mathjax/latest/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML&quot; type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;hi&quot;&gt;Hi!&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are seeing this page, it’s likely that you recieved a request from me for writing me a letter of recommendation. I’d like
to take some of your time to explain why I am a good candidate for your recommendation. I have broken said explanation 
into convenient parts so that you can have a easier, and hopefully coherent understanding of my qualifications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#professional&quot;&gt;Professional&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#academic&quot;&gt;Academic&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#personal&quot;&gt;Personal&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;professional&quot;&gt;Professional&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;positions&quot;&gt;Positions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have had the great opporotunity to intern in several research intensive positions. My first experience in an industrial setting 
was as a MAGNet Intern at the State Farm Research and Development Center (SFRDC). At this internship I learned much about the practical
decisions that come with analyzing data. I acquired skills in server-side and data management technologies such as hadoop/hbase and 
getting a first look at developing server-side applications in R using Shiny. I also developed professional skills such as report writing, consulting, and 
(most importantly) presenting research findings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a year at the SFRDC, I decided (after taking the excellent Bioinformatics course by Professor Zhao) to move over to the Dow AgroScience research
park office to work as a Bioinformatics Data Scientist. This position required learning about new and exciting developments in genetic engineering, crop science, and bioinformatics methodology.  Projects that I completed include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;building a sample size estimation application in Shiny and developing the server-side application to host such an application&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;developing a command line utility to search for zinc finger nucleases in pDAB files.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;building, validating, and developing penalized high-dimensional regression models for RNAseq data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The time at this internship taught me much about applied bioinformatics, but also gave me a great opporotunity to develop programming skills in
R and python, which has proven to be extremely useful in my work. I also gained insight into the work currently being accomplished in genetics in 
general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;academic&quot;&gt;Academic&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;research-interests&quot;&gt;Research Interests&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, I have found two complementary areas of research that are remarkably interesting to me. Working with my brother (who is a PhD in Cognitive
Neuroscience) on some projects, I have stumbled upon the growing usage of Functional Data Analysis (fda) in modeling physiological and neuroimaging data. 
I have found that there are gaps currently in the application of fda in Electroencephalogram (EEG) research. Specifically, there is much interest in Event Related Potential (ERP) methods that could effectively explain contrasts between conditions in the average amplitude of a set of EEG signals. For example, given a task in which one is presented with a stimuli that is meant to produce a statistically significant change in the amplitude of the EEG signals at some time point, where the change likely continues for some interval. While changepoint analysis is a very well researched area for time series data, physiological data like EEG measurements lack an established theory for optimal tests of changepoints when smoothness of the data is inherent. Moreover, there are also gaps in the literature in modeling function-on-scalar regression when the response is multivariate. This is very much the case in EEG research, where we can view the response of EEG amplitude to be multivariate where the dimension of the response is determined by the number of electrodes used in an experiment. Likewise, there is an inherent issue of spatial correlation in neurophysiological/neuroimaging data, where measurements taken over the brain have an inherent spatial correlation likely determined partially by the underlying neural networks that exist in the brain. Spatially correlated functional data is a very new area of research. Understanding these and building substantive modeling strategies could potentially help practitioners develop richer theories of cognitive function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much like how next generation sequencing has ushered in a new era of quantitative methods for biology, new technologies for neuroscience in general have brought quantitative individuals to the forefront of developing new tools for the brain sciences. Moreover, these methodologies are likely to have more general application, and much like other applications throughout the history of statistical sciences, will inspire new ways to view random processes in new and exciting ways. Also, while I treasure the theoretical background that the UIUC statistics department has given to me, I also want to develop practically relevant tools for practitioners, towards this goal, I have dedicated much time in developing software building skills in R Python and C++ (all of which can be found on my github page).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, I have a personal stake in this research. My sister-in-law is currently in a high risk group for early development of Multiple Sclerosis. This has obviously created a huge amount of distress for my family. There is a great need for what some call Neuro-Quants. Early detection of many diseases tends to lead to better outcomes, and MS is no different. However, there are not many good personalized medicine tools for determining courses of action based on neuroimaging data. This is a active area of research that I want to contribute to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;appointments&quot;&gt;Appointments&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, I am a Teaching Assistant for the introductory statistical methods course for graduate students in the Crop Science department, CPSC 440. This appointment has required me to produce educational materials for students, comprising of practical lessons in statistical script writing, to theoretical lessons on experimental design. I have learned alot in the process of teaching (especially about experiment design). Thanks Professor Lipka!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;personal&quot;&gt;Personal&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have come a long way at UIUC. I hopefully will leave a postive impact. I started the first and only Muay Thai club with well over 50 active members, practices 3 times a week, and started the first ever grant for university students who would like to compete at the amateur level. I have managed this for over a year, and will hopefully be able to pass this down to a community of students who care sincerely about the culture of Muay Thai. I am also an active competitor (my next fight is Febuary 6th!), and yes I understand the irony of wanting to help battle against neuro degenerative diseases while taking part in a sport that (almost surely) results in mild cognitive impairment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Concluding, I hope that this has helped to establish a better understanding of my qualifications, both academic and professional. Please let me know if you would like any more information about my recent experiences. I hope that this page has helped you decide to write me a letter of recommendation. If not however, thank you for taking time out of your busy schedule to read this page.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>About</title>
   <link href="http://kylenpayne.github.io/2015/12/02/about/"/>
   <updated>2015-12-02T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <id>http://kylenpayne.github.io/2015/12/02/about</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Thanks for visiting my personal website. I am currently a Masters Student in Statistics at the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign. I have held research
positions at State Farm, Dow Agroscience, and the Beckman Institute. I am currently looking for Ph.D. programs in Biostatistics.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Introducing Poole</title>
   <link href="http://kylenpayne.github.io/2014/01/02/introducing-poole/"/>
   <updated>2014-01-02T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <id>http://kylenpayne.github.io/2014/01/02/introducing-poole</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Strange Case of Dr. Jekyll and Mr. Hyde&lt;/em&gt; tells the story of a lawyer investigating the connection of two persons, Dr. Henry Jekyll and Mr. Edward Hyde. Chief among the novel’s supporting cast is a man by the name of Mr. Poole, Dr. Jekyll’s loyal butler.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Poole is the butler for &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;, the static site generator. It’s designed and developed by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/mdo&quot;&gt;@mdo&lt;/a&gt; to provide a clear and concise foundational setup for any Jekyll site. It does so by furnishing a full vanilla Jekyll install with example templates, pages, posts, and styles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are currently two themes built on Poole:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://hyde.getpoole.com&quot;&gt;Hyde&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lanyon.getpoole.com&quot;&gt;Lanyon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learn more and contribute on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/poole&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;whats-included&quot;&gt;What’s included&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Poole is a streamlined Jekyll site designed and built as a foundation for building more meaningful themes. Poole, and every theme built on it, includes the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Complete Jekyll setup included (layouts, config, &lt;a href=&quot;/404.html&quot;&gt;404&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/atom.xml&quot;&gt;RSS feed&lt;/a&gt;, posts, and &lt;a href=&quot;/about&quot;&gt;example page&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mobile friendly design and development&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Easily scalable text and component sizing with &lt;code&gt;rem&lt;/code&gt; units in the CSS&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Support for a wide gamut of HTML elements&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Related posts (time-based, because Jekyll) below each post&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Syntax highlighting, courtesy Pygments (the Python-based code snippet highlighter)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additional features are available in individual themes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;browser-support&quot;&gt;Browser support&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Poole and its themes are by preference a forward-thinking project. In addition to the latest versions of Chrome, Safari (mobile and desktop), and Firefox, it is only compatible with Internet Explorer 9 and above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;download&quot;&gt;Download&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Poole is developed on and hosted with GitHub. Head to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/poole/poole&quot;&gt;GitHub repository&lt;/a&gt; for downloads, bug reports, and features requests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Why you should write me a letter of recommendation</title>
   <link href="http://kylenpayne.github.io/2014/01/01/example-content/"/>
   <updated>2014-01-01T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <id>http://kylenpayne.github.io/2014/01/01/example-content</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h6 id=&quot;hi&quot;&gt;Hi!&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are seeing this page, it’s likely that you recieved a request from me for writing me a letter of recommendation. I’d like
to take some of your time to explain why I am a good candidate for your recommendation. I have broken said explanation 
into convenient parts so that you can have a easier, and hopefully coherent understanding of my qualifications.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
